Guide to the Edmund Ware Sinnott Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edmund Ware Sinnott papers
1904-1968
MS 452
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
16.75
(34 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, lectures, speeches, writings, notes, clippings, and printed material, primarily relating to Edmund Sinnott's professional career as a botanist.
Sinnott, Edmund W. (Edmund Ware), 1888-1958
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edmund Sinnott, 1956; Mrs. Sinnott, 1968; Southern Connecticut State University, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1924-1968. II. Subject Files, 1925-1964. III. Brookhaven National Laboratory Files, 1946-1950.
Biographical / Historical
Edmund Ware Sinnott received an A.B. degree from Harvard University in 1908, an A.M. in 1910, and a Ph.D. in 1913. He was on the faculty of Harvard University from 1908 to 1915. Sinnott was a professor of botany at the Connecticut Agricultural College from 1915 to 1928; at Barnard College from 1928 to 1939; at Columbia University from 1939 to 1940; and at Yale University from 1940 to 1956. At Yale he also served as chairman of the biology department, 1940-1950; director of the Sheffield Scientific School, 1945-1956; and dean of the Graduate School, 1950-1956. Sinnott died on January 6, 1968.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, lectures, speeches, writings, notes, clippings, and printed material, primarily relating to Edmund Sinnott's professional career as a botanist.
Botany -- Study and teaching; Science; Botanists; Sinnott, Edmund W. (Edmund Ware), 1888-1958; Barnard College -- Faculty; Columbia University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1924-1968, Series I
  - General
    - A, 1928-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 9)
    - Avery, George S., 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 10 - 11)
    - B, 1927-1936 (Box 1, Folder 12 - 20)
    - B, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 21 - 24)
    - Blakeslee, A. F., 1932-1934 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - C, 1927-1940 (Box 2, Folder 26 - 35)
    - College entrance exam, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - D, 1927-1934 (Box 2, Folder 37 - 40)
    - D, 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 41 - 45)
    - E - F, 1927-1940 (Box 3, Folder 46 - 55)
    - G, 1927-1940 (Box 3, Folder 56 - 64)
    - H - J, 1927-1940 (Box 4, Folder 65 - 73)
    - Journal of Botany, American, 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - K - L, 1927-1940 (Box 4, Folder 75 - 84)
    - M, 1927-1940 (Box 5, Folder 85 - 94)
    - N - O, 1927-1940 (Box 5, Folder 95 - 102)
    - P, 1927-1940 (Box 5, Folder 103 - 112)
    - R, 1927-1940 (Box 6, Folder 113 - 120)
    - S, 1927-1940 (Box 6, Folder 121 - 130)
    - T - V, 1927-1940 (Box 7, Folder 131 - 140)
    - W - Z, 1927-1940 (Box 7, Folder 141 - 151)
    - Miscellaneous, 1924-1935 (Box 8, Folder 152 - 154)
  - Select
    - A - B, 1950-1951 (Box 9, Folder 155)
    - Biology Abstracts, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 156)
    - The Biology of the Spirit, 1955-1956, undated (Box 9, Folder 157 - 159)
    - "Botany: Principles and Problems", 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 160)
    - Cell and Psyche, 1945-1956, undated (Box 9, Folder 161 - 162)
    - Comments on publications, 1943-1956, undated (Box 9, Folder 163 - 166)
    - Congregational churches
      - A, 1958-1962 (Box 10, Folder 167)
      - B, 1958-1962 (Box 10, Folder 168 - 170)
      - C, 1958-1962 (Box 10, Folder 171)
      - D, 1960-1962 (Box 10, Folder 172)
      - E, 1958-1962 (Box 10, Folder 173)
      - F, 1958-1962 (Box 10, Folder 174)
      - G, 1960-1962 (Box 10, Folder 175)
      - H, 1958-1962 (Box 10, Folder 176 - 177)
      - J - K, 1960-1961 (Box 10, Folder 178)
      - L, 1958-1966 (Box 10, Folder 179)
      - M, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 180)
      - N, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 181 - 182)
      - O, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 183)
      - P, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 184)
      - R, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 185)
      - S, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 186 - 187)
      - T, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 188)
      - U - V, 1960-1962 (Box 11, Folder 189)
      - W, 1958-1962 (Box 11, Folder 190 - 191)
      - Y, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 192)
    - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station
      - General, 1929-1954 (Box 12, Folder 193)
      - Board of Control, 1960-1964 (Box 12, Folder 194)
    - Connecticut Botanical Society, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 195)
    - Growth, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 196)
    - "Jed", 1960-1963 (Box 12, Folder 197 - 198)
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1949-1951 (Box 12, Folder 199)
    - New York Botanical Gardens, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 200)
    - Old Woodbury Historical Society, 1950-1955 (Box 12, Folder 201)
    - Positions, 1949-1950 (Box 12, Folder 202)
    - The Saturday Review, 1953-1956 (Box 12, Folder 203)
    - Science and Religion, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 204)
    - "Science and the Whole Man", 1947-1948 (Box 12, Folder 205)
    - Sinnott, E.W., 1939-1945 (Box 12, Folder 206)
    - Sugar research, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 207)
    - Sympathy, letters of, 1950-1957 (Box 12, Folder 208)
    - "Ten Million Scientists", 1949-1950 (Box 13, Folder 209)
    - Thank yous, 1950-1951 (Box 13, Folder 210)
    - "Two Roads to Truth"
      - General, 1953-1954 (Box 13, Folder 211 - 213)
      - Clippings, printed material, undated (Box 13, Folder 214)
    - University business, 1948-1951 (Box 13, Folder 215)
    - Viking Press, 1951-1952 (Box 13, Folder 216)
  - Chronological
    - 1938-1941 (Box 13, Folder 217 - 221)
    - 1942-1950 (Box 14, Folder 222 - 234)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 15, Folder 235 - 243)
    - 1954-1958 (Box 16, Folder 244 - 259)
    - 1959-1962 (Box 17, Folder 260 - 277)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 18, Folder 278 - 292)
    - 1965-1968, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 293 - 307)
- Subject Files, 1925-1964, Series II
  - Address: "The Past as Prelude", undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Autobiography, 1954 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Bibliography A - Z, undated (Box 20, Folder 3 - 4)
  - Biology abstracts, 1925-1927 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Book reviews, 1959, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Cambrian research, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Cell sizes, undated (Box 20, Folder 8 - 9)
  - Data: squash, undated (Box 20, Folder 10 - 11)
  - Dedications, writings, 1953-1954, undated (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Department of Plant Science: reports, 1955-1956 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Drafts
    - "Biological Basis", undated (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Loofa sponge, 1942-1943 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Pattern of Life, undated (Box 21, Folder 16 - 17)
    - Problem of Organic Form, undated (Box 21, Folder 18 - 19)
    - Reaction Wood, 1951-1952 (Box 21, Folder 20)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 21, Folder 21 - 22)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 22, Folder 23 - 31)
  - Epidermis
    - Connecticut Field, undated (Box 23, Folder 32)
    - Ovary, undated (Box 23, Folder 33 - 34)
  - Graphs: Lagenaria, undated (Box 23, Folder 35)
  - Greene, Stephen [lectures], 1959 (Box 23, Folder 36)
  - Honorary degrees, 1946-1954 (Box 23, Folder 37)
  - Lectures, 1945-1955 (Box 23, Folder 38 - 41)
  - Lectures, 1958-1964, undated (Box 24, Folder 42 - 47)
  - Northeastern Fiftieth Anniversary, 1948-1949 (Box 24, Folder 48)
  - "Pattern of Life" [manuscript], 1945 (Box 24, Folder 49)
  - Pedicel ratios, undated (Box 24, Folder 50)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 24, Folder 51 - 52)
  - Pressed leaves, undated (Box 25, Folder 53)
  - Printed material
    - Religion and science, 1950-1954, undated (Box 25, Folder 54 - 55)
    - Miscellaneous, 1902-1956 (Box 25, Folder 56 - 58)
  - Resolutions Committee, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 59)
  - Science and religion, undated (Box 25, Folder 60 - 61)
  - Scientific notes, 1941-1946 (Box 26, Folder 62)
  - Sheffield centennial, 1947 (Box 26, Folder 63)
  - Speeches, lectures, 1933-1952 (Box 26, Folder 64 - 66)
  - Squash, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 67)
  - Watermelon, 1935-1936 (Box 26, Folder 68 - 69)
  - Yale University business, 1941-1945 (Box 26, Folder 70)
  - F2SPx103 (42): 1-65 complete, undated (Box 26, Folder 71)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 26, Folder 72)
- Brookhaven National Laboratory Files, 1946-1950, Series III
  - Administrative progress report, 1947 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Biological and medical research conference, 1947-1949, undated (Box 27, Folder 2 - 5)
  - Budget estimates, 1948-1950 (Box 27, Folder 6 - 7)
  - Contracts, 1947 (Box 27, Folder 8 - 9)
  - Contracts, 1947-1948 (Box 28, Folder 10 - 17)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1949, undated (Box 29, Folder 18 - 24)
  - Ecology survey, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 25)
  - Engineering planning and program, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 26)
  - Facilities budget, 1950 (Box 29, Folder 27)
  - Financial papers, 1948, undated (Box 29, Folder 28)
  - Life Sciences Advisory Committee, 1948-1949 (Box 29, Folder 29 - 31)
  - Minutes, 1946-1949 (Box 29, Folder 32 - 36)
  - Monthly statements, 1948 (Box 30, Folder 37)
  - Physical Science Advisory Committee, 1948 (Box 30, Folder 38)
  - Preliminary organization, 1947 (Box 30, Folder 39 - 43)
  - Program for medicine and biology, 1947 (Box 30, Folder 44)
  - Program reports, 1946-1948 (Box 30, Folder 45 - 47)
  - Progress report, 1947 (Box 31, Folder 48)
  - Reports: miscellanea, undated (Box 31, Folder 49)
  - Statements of expenditures, 1948-1949 (Box 31, Folder 50 - 57)
  - Statements of expenditures, 1949 (Box 32, Folder 58 - 61)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1947-1949 (Box 32, Folder 62 - 63)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-073
  - Correspondence
    - 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks
    - Classes
      - Botany 9 [class notes], undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Botany/biology, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Zoology, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Lectures and botanic notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Logs
        - Leaf traces, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - Sunflowers, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Notes on/from books and speeches, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Writings, speeches, 1945-1948, 1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Personal [includes miscellaneous printed material and photographs], 1947-1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)